from Scatteren. The standard formula is
a solveny 2 podcast for UK and European
insurance professionals. Join us as
Scatteren partner Robert Chaplan leads
conversations with industry
practitioners and explores Solveny 2
developments that matter to you.
>> Welcome back to the Standard Formula
podcast. This episode continues our
global series on credential requirements
forming part of our forthcoming
encyclopedia of credential solveny.
Today is a special additional episode
following the success of our central and
Latin America series done last
September. Welcome to our discussion of
the credential solveny regime of
Colombia.
Joining me today to navigate this regime
is my colleague Caroline Jaffer. looking
forward to discussing this fascinating
jurisdiction with you, Caroline. Could
you please start us off by giving us
some background as to the credential
solveny landscape in Colombia?
>> Thanks, Rob. Certainly. Before we begin,
our thanks go out to our good friends at
Posera Ruiz for their input and feedback
on today's podcast. The insurance sector
in Colombia remains modest relative to
the size of the broader financial
system, but it is growing. Colombia's
insurance sector is regulated by the
Superintendencia Finier de Colombia or
SFC which also regulates other financial
institutions such as banks, pensions
funds, securities and the stock market.
The SFC has wide ranging powers with
responsibility for licensing and
supervision but also for consumer
protection and regulatory development
and enforcement. The Ministry of Finance
also retains policymaking powers and is
in charge of broader regulations
applicable to the insurance sector.
Colombia has increasingly aligned its
supervisory and credential systems to
international standards in recent years.
The SFC became a member of the
International Association of Insurance
Supervisors or IAS and multilateral
memorandum of understanding in 2022.
Accordingly, Colombian regulation
follows all their guidelines
specifically regarding credential
supervision, market conduct, corporate
governance and risk management. The
regulatory framework for the insurance
sector in Colombia can be found in a
single statutory regime. Specifically,
the estuto
system
together with a unified set of decrees
compiled by means of decree 2555
of 2010.
Total GWP in Colombia is projected to
reach 8.9 billion US this year. So not
an ins insubstantial market and it is
projected to grow over 11.5 billion by
2028.
In short, Colombia is a growing
insurance market has an active regulator
pursuing reformatory opportunities and
is gradually shifting towards a
riskbased model.
>> Caroline, that's really interesting.
We've started to see a pattern develop
on foreign reinsurers in jurisdictions.
How does Colombia approach this issue?
>> Colombia's approach to overseas insurers
and reinsurers largely aligns with the
market access conditions in other
nations nearby. Colombian insurance
regulation operates on the principle
that only authorized and doiciled
insurers may conduct insurance business
within Colombia. Insurers operating
Colombia must be locally incorporated
and must obtain a license from the SFC.
Much like other jurisdictions in Latin
America, foreign insurers cannot operate
in country without establishing a
presence either by setting up a
subsidiary or by registering a branch
and require formal formal approval from
the SFC to do so. In practice, most
foreign entrance form a subsidiary so
they can operate locally. For any
branches of foreign insurers, the
underlying capital backing the relevant
liabilities must be assets within
Colombia. Regarding reinsurers, the SFC
also maintains a public registry for
reinsurers known as the registry of
foreign insurers and reinsurance
intermediaries or the coex per its local
acronym that allows foreign reinsurers
to conduct business in Colombia subject
to their satisfaction of certain
eligibility requirements. Currently over
200 world reinsurers are part of the
arrays.
>> Thanks Caroline. Could you also please
give us an overview of the Colombian
regime? How much is it like solveny 2 or
not?
>> Gladly. Since 2010, Colombia's insurance
regulatory environment has been
gradually shifting to risk to a
riskbased solveny framework. Insurers
must show that their patrimony technical
equivalent of the minimum capital
requirement is at least equal to their
patrimono adquo equivalent of the Sonyy
capital requirement taking into account
underwriting assets and market risks and
more recently operational risks. The SFC
initially applied fixed minimum capital
requirements for insurers which vary
depending on the type of insurance
business. However, in more recent years,
Colombia has transitioned towards a more
riskbased capital model. The move
towards a riskbased model means insurers
in Colombia are able to calculate their
required capital based on the risk they
face such as asset risk, underwriting
risk, and other exposures.
The minimum capital for incorporation of
insurers is set by statute from time to
time but is comprised of paid in capital
reserves and retained earnings less
certain applicable deductions. This
formula will no doubt begin to now be
familiar to listeners. In respect of
technical reserves, insurers must also
maintain these covering ongoing risk and
inforce liabilities, outstanding claims,
premium deficiency and deviation.
Currently the insurance sector is
working with the government to migrate
to a more extensive adoption of solveny
2. Not only regarding the quantitive
requirements of financial strength of
capital but also focusing on pillars two
and three regarding governance, risk
management, reporting and transparency.
One of the challenges in the full
adoption of Sony 2 has been the
availability of data to assess adequate
capital requirements. To prevent risks
associated with abrupt adoption, the
Colombian government has fostered
capacity building within the insurance
sector to ensure an ordered transition.
>> Thanks, Caroline. Presumably, there's
also a provision for technical reserves.
>> Absolutely. In accordance with recent
regulations, such technical reserves
must be calculated by insurers
established and adjusted on a monthly
basis. In addition, Colombia has been
introducing legislation to align its
method of calculating such technical
reserves with international standards.
Recent regulations mandated that
insurance companies adopt IFRS17 in
place of IFRS4. These regulations were
initially aimed to apply beginning
January 2027, but in the month of March
2026, the Colon government extended the
adoption deadline to January 2028.
As of 2024, insurers are required to
calculate such reserves on a monthly
basis and adjust accordingly. The
reserves themselves must be backed by
appropriate assets positioned to an
investment policy adopted by the board
of each insurance company.
Specifically, under this framework,
assets are awaited by credit risk and
factors for underwriting volume with
reserves also included in the
calculation. The SFC's oversight ensures
that an insurers's equity and qualifying
subordinated debt cover this required
capital. The Colombian system also
emphasizes stress testing as part of its
regulatory practices, running regular
solveny trust to gauge the resilience of
insurers and the financial system as a
whole. While Colombia might not yet have
a solveny style model in full, it
employs a tailored riskbased approach
and practice which is a significant
shift.
>> Thanks Caroline. As one final point,
what is the approach to
crossjurisdictional reinsurance in
Colombia?
>> In Colombia, domestic insurers are able
to seed risks to foreign reinsurers, but
those reinsurers must be registered and
listed in the Rioex as pre previously
described. Interestingly, if a Colombian
seedant places reinsurance with a
foreign reinsurer that is not registered
with the SFC, then for regulatory
purposes, the seedant cannot produce its
provisions to that seeded risk.
Effectively, it must retain 100% of the
risk. This creates a strong incentive to
use registered reinsurers. Foreign
reinsurers wishing to establish a local
branch of Colombia must comply with
credential requirements similar to
domestic reinsurers.
>> So much to think about then for insurers
looking to enter into crossber
reinsurance transactions.
>> Absolutely. Overall, Colombia has made
significant strides in strengthening its
credential framework over the years and
it it is moving towards the more
flexible framework seen in Solveny 2.
Thank you, Caroline. It's been great
speaking with you and that brings us to
the end of today's episode. We hope that
you've enjoyed this episode and please
do reach out with any thoughts or
questions. Until next time,
>> thank you for joining us on The Standard
Formula. If you enjoyed this
conversation, be sure to subscribe in
your favorite podcast app so you don't
miss any future episodes. Additional
information about Scatteren can be found
at scatteren.com.
The Standard Formula is a podcast by
Scatteren, ARP, Slate, Marinflamm LLP,
and affiliates. Scatteren is recognized
for its deep experience in representing
insurance and reinsurance companies and
their advisers on a wide variety of
transactional and regulatory matters.
This podcast is provided for educational
andformational purposes only and is not
intended and should not be construed as
legal advice. This podcast is considered
advertising under applicable state laws.